A Guide to the Paul Ehrlich papers FA135
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Letters announcing memberships to national and international societies (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Medical Society of Iekaterinoslaw, Honorary Member, 1910 November 25; 24
  - The Dermatological Society of Vienna, Honorary Member, telegram and letter, 1910 December 14; 26
  - The Medical Society of Serbia, Belgrade, Honorary Member, 1910 December 21; 27
  - Society of Pediatricians, St. Petersburg, Honorary Member, 1911 January 19; 28
  - Imperial Society of Medicine, Constantinople, Honorary Member, 1911 February 18; 29
  - Royal Swedish Society of Sciences, Uppsala, Honorary Member, 1911 April 22; 30
  - Romanian Academy of Sciences, Honorary Member, 1911 June 16; 31
  - Honorary Citizen of Strehlen, 1911 November 16; 32
  - Society of Physicians in Smolensk, Honorary Member, 1911 November 17; 33
  - Society of Microbiology of the Netherlands, Corr. Member, 1911 November 27; 34
  - Royal Medical Society, Edinburgh, Honorary Member, 1911 December 19; 35
  - Royal Academy of Medicine of Belgium, Honorary Foreign Member, 1911 December 30; 36
  - Royal Academy of Medicine of Belgium, letter signed by King Albert of Belgium, 1911 December 30; 37
  - The Physical-Medical Society of Saratow, Honorary Member, 1911 December 14; 38
  - Society of Veterinarians of the Veterinary Institute Kharkov, Honorary Member, 1912 March 28; 39
  - National University of Athens, Honorary Doc. with a signature by the Chairman of the Department of Medicine, 1912 April 3; 40
  - National University of Athens, Honorary Doc. signed by the Rector of the University, 1912 April 3; 41
  - Committee on Cancer Research in Baden, Honorary Member, 1912 April 3; 42
  - National Academy of Medicine, Venezuela, Corr. Foreign Member, 1912 April 18; 43
  - Society of Dermatologists of Odessa, Honorary Member, 1912 April 29; 44
  - Honorary Citizen of Strehlen, letter, 1912 May 12; 45
  - Society of Dermatologists of Brazil, Honorary President (3 items: 45, 45A, 45E), 1912 May 31; 46; 3 items
  - Royal Society of Medicine and Natural Sciences, Brussels, Honorary Member, 1912 November 6; 47
  - German Society of Recreation Homes for Merchants, Member of the Committee, 1912 November 8; 48
  - Society of Natural Sciences, Braunschweig, Honorary Member, 1913 February 11; 49
  - Orlof Medical Society, Honorary Member, 1913 March 10; 50
  - Kazan Veterinary Institute, Honorary Member, 1913 March 31; 52
  - Society of Physicians, Odessa, Honorary Member, 1913 July 10; 53
  - Society of German Neurologists, Honorary Member, 1913 October 3; 54
  - Society of Dermatologists of Italy, Honorary Member, 1913 December 17; 55
  - Society of Biology, France, Honorary Member, 1913 December 28; 56
  - Society of Jewish Physicians of the Ottoman Empire, Honorary Member, 1914 March 4; 57
  - Medical-Surgical Society of Bologna, Corr. Foreign Member, 1914 March 31; 58
  - German Pharmaceutical Society, Honorary Member, 1915 July 13; 59
- Letters in connection with orders received by Paul Ehrlich
  (Arranged in chronological order).
  - "Kronen Orden", 3rd class, given by Wilhelm II handwritten letters, 1899; 3 letters (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - from Wilhelm with signature, 1899 September 2; 1
    - from the minister, 1899 September 7; 2
    - from the office of the General Ordens Commission, granting the patent, 1899 October 17; 3
  - "St. Olaf Orden", 2nd class, given by Oscar, King of Norway and Sweden, handwritten letters, 1900; 4 letters (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - letter signed by King Oscar, announcing the order, 1900 September 29; 1
    - official translation, 2
    - letter from the minister allowing acceptance and permission to wear the order, 1900 December 31; 3
    - letter thanking the Swedish government for the order (not Ehrlich's handwriting), 4
  - "Dannebrog Orden", 2nd class, given by the King of Denmark, handwritten letters, 1901; 3 letters (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - letter from the Royal Danish Order Chancellor, 1901 July 16; 1
    - official translation, 2
    - letter from the minister (signed by Althoff) allowing the acceptance and permission to wear the order, 1901 November 14; 3
  - "Great Gold Medal of Science", given by Wilhelm II, handwritten letters, 1903; 2 letters (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - letter from the minister, announcing the award, 1903 December 12; 1
    - "Bescheiningung", 1903 December 12; 2
  - "Roter Adler Orden", 3rd class, given by Wilhelm II, handwritten letters, 1906; 2 letters (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - letter signed by Wilhelm, announcing the order, 1906 September 2; 1
    - letter from the Ordenskommission, 1906 October 29; 2
  - "Ritterkreuz des Ordens Berthold I von Baden", 1907 February 5 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    letter signed by Friedrich, Grand Duke of Baden.
  - "Kronen Orden", 2nd class, 1910 January 18 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    letter signed by Wilhelm II.
  - "St. Sava Orden", given by King Peter of Serbia, (letters with envelopes, calling card, diploma), 1910 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - letter of translation from the Serbian legation, 1911 January 8; 1
    - diploma with envelope from Peter I, 1910 August 14; 2
    - Letter by Paul Ehrlich to Serbia legation, 1910 December 3; 3; Typescript
    - letter from the minister with envelope, 1911 March 24; 4
  - "St. Anna Orden", 1st class with diamonds given by the Emperor of Russia, 1911; 3 letters, 2 handwritten (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - letter in Russian, 1911; 1
    - letter from the minister allowing the acceptance and granting permission to wear the order, 1911 August 26; 2
    - "Besitzurkunde", diploma of ownership by the minister, 1911 September 26; 3
  - "Grosskreuz des Zivilordens Alfons XII", given by Alfons XIII, King of Spain, 1911; 5 letters (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - letter in Spanish announcing the order, 1910 December 2; 1
    - official translation, 1911 February 17; 2
    - diploma in Spanish, 1911 February 1; 3
    - letter from the minister, granting permission, 1911 April 26; 4
  - "Orden der Büste des Bolivar", 2nd class given by the President of Venezuela, 1911; 6 letters (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - diploma in Spanish, March 28, 1911, with envelope, 1911 March 28; 1
    - letter in Spanish announcing the order, 1911 March 28; 2
    - Letter from the Venezuelan legation in German, 1911 April 25; 3; Typescript
    - Letter by Paul Ehrlich, 1911 April 26; 4; Typescript
    - letter from the minister allowing acceptance and granting permission to wear the order (handwritten) with envelope, 1911 June 23; 5
    - Venezuelan official newspaper with report of the order given to Paul Ehrlich, 6
  - "Maximilians Orden", given by the King of Bavaria, 1912; 6 letters, handwritten and typescript (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - diploma, 1912 November 26; 1
    - Letter from the Bavarian Embassy, 1912 November 28; 2; Typescript
    - letter from the minister requesting that Paul Ehrlich ask permission to receive the order, 1912 December 24; 3
    - letter from the minister granting permission, 1913 February 18; 4
    - handwritten letter listing new members, 5
    - 2 pamphlets with by-laws and members of the order, 6
  - "Roter Adler Orden", 2nd class, given by Wilhelm II handwritten, 1914; 2 letters (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - letter announcing the order from the King of Prussia, not signed by Wilhelm II, 1914 January 27; 1
    - letter from the office of "Geheimes Zivil Kabinett", 1914 January 27; 2
  - "Cross of the Meritul Sanitar", 1st class, given by the King of Romania, 1914; 5 letters, handwritten and typescript (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - diploma, March 3, 1914 (is in map Folder 46), 1914 March 3; 1
    - Patent from the Romanian Consulate, 1914 October 22; 2; Typescript
    - Letter from the Romanian Minister of Interior, 1914 March 19; 3; Typescript
    - translation, 4
    - letter from the Minister allowing acceptance and granting permission to wear the order March 25, 1915, 1914; 5
  - "Order of the Rising Sun", from Japan 1 diploma in Japanese, 1911 March 14; Map folder 46 (Folder 46)
- Manuscripts and speeches
  - Paul Ehrlich's doctoral dissertation, "Beiträge zur Theorie und Praxis der histologischen Färbung", 1878 June 17; typewritten, 65 pages (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Lecture given by Ehrlich about cobra venom, undated (1901-1902?); 4 pages, typescript manuscript (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - "Über Toxine und Antitoxine", published in Therapie der Gegenwart, 1901; lecture at the 13th International Medical Congress in Paris, August 4, 1900, section for bacteriology; 46 handwritten pages by Ehrlich (the last 2 pages are not in his hand). With this manuscript are 14 handwritten pages, not Ehrlich's, entitled "Anmerkungen" (maybe by Martha Marquardt) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Handwritten manuscript of a speech by Ehrlich at the death of Carl Weigert, (Weigert died August 5, 1904), 23 pages in Ehrlich's handwriting, 2 typescript copies of same speech, 10 pages each. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Address at the inauguration of Georg Speyer-Haus, in Frankfurt, 1906 September 6; 3 typescript manuscripts (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - manuscript (draft) with many corrections in Ehrlich's handwriting, 31 pages, 1
    - typescript manuscript with corrections made, 28 pages (may have been made by M. Marquardt for Himmelweit), 2
    - typescript manuscript of corrected speech, not complete, 25 pages only, 3
  - "Über Immunität mit besonderer Berücksichtigung der Beziehung zwischen Vertheilung und Wirkung der Antigene", Harben Lecture, delivered in London 1907, published in Beiträge zur experimentellen Pathologie und Chemotherapie, 1909; 38 typescript pages (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "Über den jetzigen Stand der Karzinomforschung", published in Beiträge zur experimentellen Pathologie und Chemotherapie, 1909, lecture given (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Lecture given by Ehrlich in Frankfurt when he was honored for the Nobel Prize (in 1908), delivered in 1909, Typescript manuscript 19 pages with some notations by Ehrlich and a typewritten copy of the minutes of this celebration (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Ehrlich's address at the Congress in Königsberg, 1910 September 20; 21 pages, typescript minutes (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Article which appeared in a jubilee number of the Wiener Medizinische Wochenschrift, 1911 dealing with Salvarsan therapy, 13 pages, some with Ehrlich's corrections, 13 pages, typescript manuscript (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Lecture given by Ehrlich at an unknown occasion (maybe in Frankfurt November/December 1910), dealing with Salvarsan therapy on a large scale, but before it was released to private physicians. Some pages are marked by Ehrlich, 1910 November-December; 49 pages, typescript manuscript (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Lecture given by Ehrlich at an unknown occasion, dealing with cases of death and blindness after treatment with 606, 24 pages with many markings and corrections in Ehrlich's handwriting, Typescript manuscript (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Lecture given by Ehrlich in London August 1912, published in Lancet, 1912, 1912 August; 24 pages typescript manuscript (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Ehrlich's talk at his 60th birthday, 1914 March 14; 5 pages, typescript manuscript (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Speech given by Ehrlich at the death of Nina Yamikoff, a scientist, undated; 2 pages typescript manuscript (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Disputes and Polemics (Box 3)
  Short description.
  (Arranged in alphabetical order).
  - "Anti Arrhenius" - dispute over the toxin-antitoxin theory (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "Dreuw Polemic" - about Salvarsan, "unfair distribution of test-material and unethical advertising" (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "Gruber Polemic" - dispute over the side-chain theory (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "Dispute with Röhl" - about the use and ownership of a laboratory protocol book (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "Uhlenhuth Polemic" - dispute over the original recognition of the chemotherapeutic value of atoxyl (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "Anti Arrhenius", 1904 May 7; Typescript manuscript, 15 pages (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Ehrlich is disputing Arrhenius' theory about mixtures of toxins and antitoxins typescript letter (1) from W. Nernst to Ehrlich, asking Ehrlich to read the enclosed manuscript by Nernst typescript manuscript by Nernst, "Über die Anwendbarkeit der Gesetze des chemischen Gleichgewichtes auf Gemische von Toxin und Antitoxin", 9 pages.
  - "Dreuw Polemic", 1910 September 11 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Handwritten letter (1) by Dreuw to Ehrlich, September 11, 1910 typescript pages (4) by Ehrlich, answering some of Dreuw's accusations typescript pages (66) by Ehrlich, recounting the development of Salvarsan and its clinical trials, in answer to Dreuw's accusations.
  - "Gruber Polemic", 88 pages, some handwritten (Franz Sachs?) with many corrections (Morgenroth?) and markings by Ehrlich (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "Dispute with Röhl" (Box 3, Folder 19)
    All typescript and the correspondence is a copy (Abschrift).
    - Verhandlung, Ehrlich describing why a cooperation with Röhl is no longer possible, 1909 June 4
    - letter by Röhl to Ehrlich in answer, Frankfurt, 1909 June 6
    - letter by Ehrlich to Röhl, Frankfurt, 1909 June 15
      (this letter may not have been sent according to a handwritten note (by Martha Marquardt?).
    - Kahn to Röhl, 1909 October 2; 1
    - Röhl to Kahn, 1909 October 2; 2
    - Kahn to Röhl, 1909 October 2; 3
    - Röhl to Kahn, 1909 October 2; 4
    - letter by Kahn to Röhl, 1909 October 3
    - letter by Kahn to Röhl, 1909 October 3
    - letter by Röhl to Kahn, 1909 October 4
    - letter by Kahn to Röhl, 1909 October 5
    - letter by Röhl to Kahn, 1909 October 12
    - letter by Kahn to Röhl, 1909 October 13
    - letter by Kahn to Röhl, 1909 October 14
    - letter by two lawyers, Dr. Levi and Dr. Hirsch to Paul Ehrlich, 1909 October 21
    - letter by Ehrlich to Röhl, 1909 October 22
    - letter by Röhl to Ehrlich, 1909 October 23
    - Gutachten - legal opinion
    - Revers - acknowledgment comments to the Gutachten by Rohl comments to the comments of Rohl by the lawyers statement to the arbitration court by Paul Ehrlich
  - "Uhlenhuth Polemic" (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Paul Ehrlich to Paul Uhlenhuth, 5 typescript letters
    - Ehrlich to Bertarelli, 1 typescript letter
    - Uhlenhuth to Ehrlich, 1906 November 6; 8 handwritten letters
    - Uhlenhuth to Ehrlich, 1908 June 18; handwritten letter
    - Ehrlich to Uhlenhuth, 1908 September 15; typescript letter
    - Uhlenhuth to Ehrlich, 1909 February 11; handwritten letter
    - Ehrlich to Uhlenhuth, 1909 February 11; typescript letter
    - Ehrlich to Bertarelli, 1909 February 11; typescript letter
    - Uhlenhuth to Ehrlich, 1909 February 21; handwritten letter
    - Uhlenhuth to Ehrlich, 1909 March 31; handwritten letter
    - Uhlenhuth to Ehrlich, 1909 May 5; handwritten letter
    - Ehrlich to Uhlenhuth, 1909 May 6; typescript letter
    - Ehrlich to Uhlenhuth, 1909 May 13; typescript letter
    - Ehrlich to Uhlenhuth, 1909 September 1; typescript letter
    - Uhlenhuth to Ehrlich, 1909 September 20; handwritten letter
    - Uhlenhuth to Ehrlich, 1909 October 18; handwritten letter
    - Uhlenhuth to Ehrlich, 1909 October 28; handwritten letter
    - 3 typescript pages from Ehrlich, each with a separate dispute of what Uhlenhuth may have said
    - 7 typescript pages by Ehrlich rebuffing the Uhlenhuth accusation that he, Uhlenhuth, deserves the right to be called the first to discover that atoxyl can cure syphilis; some pages have corrections but not in Ehrlich's handwriting
    - Ehrlich: Schlusswort, 2 typescript pages
    - 4 newspaper clippings dealing with Salvarsan, Ehrlich and Uhlenhuth, all, 1910 November
    - Die Chemotherapie der Spirollosen, 1911 March 20
      Reprint of article sent to Ehrlich for correction.
    - Zu den vorstehenden Bemerkungen von Paul Uhlenhuth, 1911 April 27
      Reprint of an article written by Uhlenhuth: Bemerkungen zu der Arbeit von Paul Ehrlich - Die Chemotherapie der Spirollosen.
- Copy Books and Transcripts
  Copy-books: there are 47 bound volumes of copies of correspondence, laboratory notes and instructions, as well as laboratory protocols. Each book has about 500 pages; many of these are copies of handwritten notes and letters by Paul Ehrlich, the other pages are copies of typewritten letters with Ehrlich's signature. Typescript: Martha Marquardt transcribed the handwritten pages and made four copies (in a few cases six copies). Three copies are in this collection, the fourth remained at the Wellcome Institute, London. Miss Marquardt divided the labeled copy-books in Series I-VI, since they overlap in time and contain copies of varying material.
  Series I: labeled: Copir Buch, are copies of correspondence
  Series II: Zettel Buch, are copies of "Blöcke" (i.e. laboratory instruction written on cardboard)
  Series III: Carcinom, are copies of notes about cancer research
  Series IV: Direcktor Ehrlich, are copies of laboratory protocol notes to co-workers and some correspondence
  Series V: Direcktor Ehrlich, are copies of correspondence and some "Blöcke"
  Series VI: Speyer-Haus, are copies of "Blöcke", laboratory instructions and protocol notes
  Each box contains the copy-book and three copies of the typescripts. Where there are more copies, they are stored in boxes labeled with an "A".
  Arranged in chronological order and by Series #.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Copy books and transcripts Boxes 4-18 are restrcited. Scholarly access is permitted to the transcript copies only (Boxes 80-86). Consult Archivist for further assistance.
  - Series I: Copir Buch II Direktor, 1898 November 11-1899 February 21 (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
  - Series I: Copir Buch III Ehrlich, 1899 February 21-1899 July 31 (Box 5)
  - Series I: Copir Buch IV, 1899 August 1-1900 March 1 (Box 6)
  - Series II: Zettel Buch I, 1900 February 1-1900 December 26 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
  - Series II: Zettel Buch II und Carcinom, 1900 December 25-1901 September 21 (Box 8)
  - Series II: Zettel Buch III, 1902 January 22-1902 December 2 (Box 9)
  - Series II: Zettel Buch IV, 1902 December 2-1903 May 11 (Box 10)
  - Series II: Zettel Buch V, 1903 May 11-1904 September 5 (Box 11)
  - Series II: Zettel Buch VI, 1904 September 5-1905 July 14 (Box 12)
  - Series II: Zettel Buch IX, 1908 July 17-1912 October 6 (Box 13)
  - Series II: Zettel Buch X, 1912 October 6-1915 May 15 (Box 14)
  - Series III: Carcinom III, 1906 December 12-1914 January 18 (Box 15)
  - Series IV: Direktor Ehrlich I, 1903 April 22-1904 December 31 (Box 16-16A)
  - Series IV: Direktor Ehrlich III, 1905 November l6-1906 November 10 (Box 17, Folder 1-3)
  - Series IV: Direktor Ehrlich IV, 1906 November 15-1909 July 10 (Box 18, Folder 1-3)
  - Series IV: Direktor Ehrlich V, 1909 July 11-1911 June 21 (Box 19)
  - Series IV: Direktor Ehrlich VII, 1912 September 14-1915 July 7 (Box 20)
  - Series V: Direktor Ehrlich IX, 1902 September 25-1902 December 23 (Box 21, Folder 1-6)
  - Series V: Direktor Ehrlich X, 1902 December 23-1903 January 26 (Box 22, Folder 1-5)
  - Series V: Direktor Ehrlich XI, 1903 March 19-1903 July 17; Mostly typescripts no transcripts (Box 23)
  - Series V: Direktor Ehrlich XIII, 1903 December 21-1904 June 13 (Box 23)
  - Series V: Direktor Ehrlich XV, 1904 October 25-1905 February 2 (Box 23)
  - Series V: Direktor Ehrlich XVI, 1905 February 6-1905 April 22 (Box 23)
  - Series V: Direktor Ehrlich XVII, 1905 April 20-1905 August 4 (Box 24)
  - Series V: Direktor Ehrlich XVIII, 1905 August 4-1906 January 1 (Box 24)
  - Series V: Direktor Ehrlich XXI, 1906 November 30-1907 May 5 (Box 24)
  - Series V: Direktor Ehrlich XXII, 1907 May 5-1907 November 1 (Box 24)
  - Series V: Direktor Ehrlich XXIII, 1907 November 1-1908 April 9 (Box 25, Folder 1-5)
  - Series V: Direktor Ehrlich XXIV, 1908 April 9-1908 October 22 (Box 25, Folder 1-5)
  - Series V: Direktor Ehrlich XXV, 1908 October 22-1909 March 29 (Box 25, Folder 1-5)
  - Series V: Direktor Ehrlich XXVI, 1909 March 29-1909 October 5 (Box 25, Folder 1-5)
  - Series V: Direktor Ehrlich XXVII, 1909 October 4-1910 March 3 (Box 26)
  - Series V: Direktor Ehrlich XXVIII, 1910 March 3-1911 April 10; page 1-300 typescript, rest Blöcke (Box 26)
  - Series V: Direktor Ehrlich XXIX, 1911 April 11-?; all handwritten Blöcke, some typewritten pages(40) (Box 26)
  - Series V: Direktor Ehrlich XXX, 1912 October 19-?; pages 1-50 typescript rest Blöcke (Box 26)
  - Series VI: Speyer-Haus I, 1906 September 18-1907 February 1 (Box 27-27A, Folder 1-5)
  - Series VI: Speyer-Haus II, 1907 February 1-1907 May 24 (Box 28-28A, Folder 1-5)
  - Series VI: Speyer-Haus III, 1907 May 25-1908 January 3 (Box 29, Folder 1-3)
  - Series VI: Speyer-Haus IV, 1908 January 3-1908 May 31 (Box 30)
  - Series VI: Speyer-Haus V, 1908 May 30-1908 October 15 (Box 31, Folder 1-3)
  - Series VI: Speyer-Haus VII, 1909 February 27-1909 October 29 (Box 32, Folder 1-3)
  - Series VI: Speyer-Haus VIII, 1909 October 30-1910 June 1 (Box 33, Folder 1-3)
  - Series VI: Speyer-Haus IX, 1910 June 2-1910 October 13 (Box 34, Folder 1-3)
  - Series VI: Speyer-Haus X, 1910 October 13-1911 July 27 (Box 34, Folder 1-3)
  - Series VI: Speyer-Haus XI, 1911 July 27-1912 August 24; pages 1-170 only (Box 36)
  - Series VI: Speyer-Haus XII, 1912 August 27-1913 May 26; no transcripts (Box 37)
  - Series VI: Speyer-Haus XIII, 1913 May 27-1915 August 1; no transcripts (Box 37)
  - Transcript Copies
    - Series I - Copy Book II Direktor (Box 80, Folder 1)
      Separated Materials
      From box 4, folders 1-3
    - Series I - Copy Book III Ehrlich (Box 80, Folder 2)
      From box 5, folders 1-3
    - Series I - Copy Book IV (Box 80, Folder 3)
      From box 6, folder 1 of 3
    - Series I - Copy Book IV (Box 81, Folder 1)
      From box 6, folders 2 & 3
    - Series II - Zettel Book I, Folders 1-3 (Box 81, Folder 2)
      From box 7, folders 1-3
    - Series II - Zettel Book II and Carcinom (Box 81, Folder 3)
      From box 8, folders 1 & 2
    - Series II - Zettel Book II and Carcinom (Box 82, Folder 1)
      From box 8, folder 3
    - Series II - Zettel Book III (Box 82, Folder 2)
      From box 9, folders 1-3
    - Series II - Zettel Book IV (Box 82, Folder 3)
      From box 10, folders 1 & 2
    - Series II - Zettel Book IV (Box 83, Folder 1)
      From box 10, folder 3
    - Series II - Zettel Book V (Box 83, Folder 2)
      From box 11, folders 1-3
    - Series II - Zettel Book VI (Box 83, Folder 3)
      From box 12, folders 1 & 2
    - Series II - Zettel Book VI (Box 84, Folder 1)
      From box 12, folder 3
    - Series II - Zettel Book IX (Box 84, Folder 2)
      From box 13, folders 1& 2
    - Series II - Zettel Book X (Box 84, Folder 3)
      From box 14, folders 1& 2
    - Series III - Carcinom Book III (Box 84, Folder 4)
      From box 15, folder 1
    - Series III - Carcinom Book III (Box 85, Folder 1)
      From box 15, folder 2
    - Series IV - Direktor, Ehrlich I (Box 85, Folder 2)
      From box 16, folders 1-3
    - Series IV - Direktor, Ehrlich I (Box 85, Folder 3)
      From box 16a, folders 1 & 2
    - Series IV - Direktor, Ehrlich I (Box 86, Folder 1)
      From box 16a, folder 3
    - Series IV - Direktor, Ehrlich III (Box 86, Folder 2)
      From box 17, folders 1-3
    - Series IV - Direktor, Ehrlich IV (Box 86, Folder 3)
      From box 18, folders 1 & 2
- Laboratory Notebooks, 1883-1912; 15 letters
  - 1883 November 15, thin black notebook with an inscription by Hedwig Ehrlich / with Blöcke glued to it; 14.1 × 19.0 × 0.5 cm. (Box 38, Folder 1)
  - 1884 February 14-December 1, thin black notebook, not in Ehrlich's handwriting (corrections may be by Ehrlich); 10.2 × 16.0 × 0.5 cm. (Box 38, Folder 2)
  - 1885 February-March, thin notebook with missing covers, with a few notes in Ehrlich's handwriting; 10.0 × 16.7 × 0.5 cm. (Box 38, Folder 3)
  - 1886 January 20-February 24, thin black notebook "Frosch-Buch", not in Ehrlich's handwriting, except 1 page, next to last; 10.3 × 16.2 × 0.5 cm. (Box 38, Folder 4)